Guide to the Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children, Yale University, records
1971-1976
RU 197
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.25
The records consist of correspondence, reports, financial papers, memoranda, sponsor forms, and case files on individual guests documenting the activities and operations of the Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children.
Yale University. Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 6 (YRG 6), Records of Yale committees.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to Series II, III, and IV is restricted.
Arrangement
The records are arranged as follows: I. Administrative and Financial Files, 1940-1948. II. Administrative and Financial Files, 1940-1946. III. Files on Sponsors, Non-Sponsors, and English Guests, 1940-1946. IV. Case Files, 1940-1945.
Biographical / Historical
The committee existed from 1940-1948 and coordinated the relocation to the United States of wives and children of Oxford and Cambridge faculty members during World War II.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, reports, financial papers, memoranda, sponsor forms, and case files on individual guests documenting the activities and operations of the Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Children; World War, 1939-1945 -- Civilian relief; Hemingway, Samuel Burdett, 1883-1958; Lovett, Sidney, 1890-1979; Purdy, Richard Little, 1904-1990; University of Cambridge -- Faculty; University of Oxford -- Faculty; Yale University. Faculty Committee on Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children
- Administrative and financial files, 1940-1948; Series I
  - Affidavits, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alien registration: correspondence, pamphlets, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applications and forms (blank), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Balliol College, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bank books: cancelled, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cambridge: correspondence, memoranda, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Camp expenses: budget sheets, school costs, 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Campaign: money raising, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Child Welfare, Division of: Hartford, Connecticut, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Children's Bureau: correspondence and memoranda re: Department of Labor Standards, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Children's Center car: milage, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Christmas gifts, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Citrus Concentrate, Incorporated: correspondence, invoices, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - College Entrance Examination Board, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cunnard White Star Limited: correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Duty on clothing, parcel post shipments to England, 1940-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Film, 8mm. color: children at Divinity School, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Financial correspondence and memoranda, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 21)
  - Financial and legal papers: 1949 Apr addition, 1941-1952 (Box 2, Folder 22 - 23)
  - Insurance, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - International Educational Council: Executive Committee meetings, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Initial reception, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lawton, Rachel: Field Worker, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - London News, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Medical bills: receipts, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - National War Fund, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - News of Children who have returned to England, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Oxford University Evacuation Trust Fund, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Publications
    - British panphlets, booklets, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - British Overseas Volunteer Appeal: pamphlets, correspondence, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - United States Committee for the Care of European Children: booklets, pamphlets, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Yale Faculty Cornittee Project: newspaper clippings, 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Receipts and disbursements, 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Reports
    - Adoption Home Study: Tentative outline, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - British Children in the United States, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Committee members: outline of duties, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Mount Kolyoke Committee for Foreign Students, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Pilgrim's Progress: recipients, contributors, Treasurer's Report, lists, 1940-1944 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Summer and Autumn, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - To the Yale Committee for Receiving Oxford and Cambridge University Children, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Resources: scholarships, real estate, entertainment (Christmas party plans), 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Rhodes Scholarship Trust, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Sailing and Airline directions, 1941-1945 (Box 5, Folder 47 - 48)
  - Social Service Index, 1940-1944 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - United States Committee for the Care of European Children
    - Forms, policies, Memoranda, 1934-1943 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Hunnybun, Noel: correspondence, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Reception: bills and receipts, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Volunteer Committee: inventory of furnishings in apartments, 1940-1944 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Weekapaug Cottage: correspondence expenses, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Check Books
    - 1940 Trustees (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - 1940-1942 Special account (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - 1940 Jun 27 - 1941 May (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - 1941 May 9 - 1941 Dec 22 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - 1941 Dec 22 - 1942 Jul 17 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - 1942 Jul 21 - 1943 Mar 1 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - 1943 Mar 1 - 1943 Oct 7 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - 1943 Oct 7 - 1944 Aug 16 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - 1944 Aug 15 - 1945 Nov 13 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - 1945 Nov 14 - 1948 May 24 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Monies brought from England ledger, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 65)
- Administrative and financial file, 1940-1946; Series II
  Conditions Governing Access
  Closed to research.
  - British Counsulate General, 1940-1945 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Confirmation classes, 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Connecticut Children's Aid Society, 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Departure memoranda, 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Educational Material re children
    - Hemingway, S.B. files, 1940-1942 (Box 9, Folder 16 - 17)
    - Lovett S. Files, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Work Sheets, plans for schools and camps, and other summer plans, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Committee: correspondence and members list, 1940-1946 (Box 9, Folder 20 - 22)
  - Financial Aid list: from 1941 campaign, 1940-1941 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Immigration and Naturalization Service of United States Department of Justice: Department of State, 1941-1944 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Letters (copies) from British mothers who have returned to England, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Lovett, Sidney: personal file, 1940-1942 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Medical care, 1940-1944 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Oxford Parents
    - Burn, Katherine: correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 28 - 30)
    - Lists, miscellaneous, 1940-1941 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Lists, original, 1940-1946 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Quarterly reports on Children, 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 33 - 35)
  - Policies, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Smith College, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Statistics, 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Swarthmore: correspondence on children, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - United States Committee for the Care of European Children
    - Correspondence re: children, 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 40 - 43)
    - Boston Branch, 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 44)
  - University of Toronto: Sub Committee for British Children, 1940-1942 (Box 11, Folder 45)
- Files on sponsors, non-sponsors and English guests, 1940-1946; Series III
  - Affidavits - cancelled, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Children and sponsors - lists, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Committee children: non-Yale, 1940-1945 (Box 12, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Legal forms: sponsors, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Original Yale Committee Group who did not come through New Haven: lists, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Possible sponsors, 1940-1941 (Box 14, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Prospective sponsors: A-S, 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 11 - 16)
  - Prospective Sponsors: T-Y, 1940-1942 (Box 15, Folder 17 - 18)
  - Special Children: Sponsor list and homes suggested, undated (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Sponsors and English guests: A-K, 1940-1945 (Box 15, Folder 20 - 25)
  - Sponsors and English guests: L-Z, 1940-1945 (Box 16, Folder 26 - 30)
  - Sponsors registration forms and correspondence, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Sponsors: withdrawn, 1940-1942 (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Summaries: children and sponsora, 1945-1946 (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Wood, Cornelius A., Cuttyhunk Cottage: Short Term sponsors, not Yale, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 34)
- Case files, 1940-1945; Series IV
- Photographs, Series V (Box 30, Folder 125)